Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Music
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William A. Speck collection of Goetheana: music
1830-1889
YCGL MSS 9
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.58
(2 boxes)
The collection, a part of the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana, consists of manuscript scores, all either settings of texts by Goethe or compositions based on, or inspired by, his works. The music manuscripts include autographs by Liszt, Carl Loewe, Mendelssohn, Johann Friedrich Reichardt, Ludwig Spohr, and Karl Friedrich Zelter. The collection includes a one-page fragment from Beethoven's Egmont Overture, Op. 84, and an early sketch from Wagner's Faust Overture.
Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of the manuscript music in the Speck Collection was assembled by William A. Speck, largely by purchase funded by the University, during the early years of the Collection's presence at Yale. Some items have been added in more recent times.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6)
WILLIAM A SPECK and THE WILLIAM A. SPECK COLLECTION OF GOETHEANA
The Speck music manuscripts are an integral part of the more extensive William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana. For biographical information on William A. Speck and a general history and description of the Speck Collection, see the finding aid for the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6).
The manuscript scores listed here are complemented in the Speck Collection by printed scores and librettos gathered on similar principles: music using texts by Goethe or inspired by his works. First editions of songs by Schubert and a copy of the "Leipziger Liederbuch," a collection of songs published by Breitkopf in 1770 and said to contain the first appearance in print of a poem by Goethe, are highpoints of this part of the Speck Collection.
Scope and Contents
The manuscript scores in the Speck Collection are all either settings of texts by Goethe or compositions based on, or inspired by, his works. Principally from the nineteenth century, the manuscripts include autographs by Liszt, Carl Loewe, Mendelssohn, Johann Friedrich Reichardt, Ludwig Spohr, and Goethe's composer friend Karl Friedrich Zelter, among others. The best-known items are a one-page fragment from Beethoven's Egmont Overture, Op. 84, (folder 2) and an early sketch from Wagner's Faust Overture (folder 3). The Egmont fragment has been described by Georg Kinsky in Die Handschriften von Beethoven's Egmont-Musik (Vienna, 1933) and more recently by Adolf Fecker in Die Entstehung von Beethoven's Musik zu Goethes Trauerspiel Egmont: eine Abhandlung über die Skizzen (Hamburg, 1978). The Wagner fragment, also a single leaf containing 2 pages, belongs to the first version of the work, titled Ouvertüre zu Goethes 'Faust', Ier Theil, completed in 1840 in Paris and later described as "Der einsame Faust (Oder: Faust in der Einsamkeit); ein Tongedicht für das Orchester"; it was considerably revised for the 1855 version, Eine Faust Ouvertüre.
The acquisition of the manuscript score of Mendelssohn's song Suleika (Op. 57, no. 3) (folder 10), a setting of a poem from Goethe's West-östlicher Divan, illustrates William Speck's often ingenious methods of pursuing Goethe materials around the world. The Mendelssohn score, as well as a number of important Goethe autographs, was acquired around 1920 from the Chicago banker and collector Oliver R. Barrett. Speck learned that Barrett had an interest in presidential autographs, and since Speck had a fairly easy source of such documents in the person of William Howard Taft, whose tenure at the Yale Law School coincided with Speck's early years as library curator, several exchanges were made: Goethe-related manuscripts for letters Taft had received from his successor, Teddy Roosevelt.
Additions are still being made to the Speck collection of music manuscripts, as opportunity allows. Recent acquisitions, 1997-2010, include manuscript scores for Carl Baermann, "An Lina. Gedicht von Goethe," Albert Moeschinger, "Katzenpastete," and Johann Gottlieb Naumann, "Auf den Auen wandlen wir."
Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 ( Egmont); Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 -- Songs and music; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Egmont); Liszt, Franz, 1811-1886; Loewe, Carl, 1796-1869; Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847; Reichardt, Johann Friedrich, 1752-1814; Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928; Spohr, Louis, 1784-1859; Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883; Zelter, Carl Friedrich, 1758-1832
- File List, 1830-1889, n.d.; 1.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  The scores are arranged alphabetically
  by composer. Works by unidentified
  composers are listed by title at the end.
  - BAERMANN, CARL
    - An Lina. Gedicht von Goethe, 1874 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Autograph ms.
      Song for solo voice and piano in
      D major, marked moderato.
      From Goethe's poem, "Liebchen kommen
      dieses Lieder, Jemasl wieder Dir zu
      Hand! Sitze beim Claviere neider, Wo
      der Freund sonst bei dir Stand.. ."
      On the bottom of the first page is
      Baermann's notation: "Auch dieses kleine
      Liedchen bittet um kleines Plätzchen der
      Erinnerung an Ihren Sie hochverehrenden,
      Carl Baermann senior, München den
      17.Mai 1874
  - BEETHOVEN, LUDWIG VAN, 1770-1827
    - [Egmont. op. 84. Clärchens Tod], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Autograph ms., fragment.
      [2] p. 23 x 32 cm.
      Page [1] contains the last 6 measures
      [32-37] of the music at the death of
      Clärchen, scored for orchestra; on
      p. [2] a notation for instrumentation
      of measures 12-14, and 16 of the
      overture, apparently preparatory for
      a clean copy. With typed ms. of a
      description by George Kinsky. [3] l.
      28 cm.
    - Musik Klärchens Tod Bezeichnend (Box 1, Folder 3)
      [9] p. 25 x 35 cm.
      A copy of Beethoven's music to
      Clärchen's Tod from his Egmont
      overture, op. 84, scored for
      orchestra.
  - HAUPTMANN, MORITZ, 1792-1868.
    - Mignon. Kennst du das Land wo die Citronen blühn... (Box 1, Folder 4)
      For solo voice with piano
      accompaniment. From Goethe's
      Ballad "Wilhelm Meister."
  - HERTZ, ALFRED, 1872-1942
    - An Die Entfernte, [18]89[?] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      [2] p. 35 cm.
      accompaniment. Words by Goethe,
      beginning: So hab' ich wirklich dich
      verloren? Note at top of p. [1],
      in blue pencil, October, 89.
  - KIENLEN, JOHANN CHRISTOPH, 1784-1830
    - Lieder aus Goethe's Faust in Musik gesetzt und einer durchlaucht dem regierenden fürsten von Carolath ehrebietungsvoll gewidmet von Kienlen, Kapellmeister des K.K. National Theaters zu Pressburg. Charlottenstrasse no. 42. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      [16] p. 25 x 34 cm.
      At bottom of t.-p. in another hand,
      610. For one voice with pianoforte
      accompaniment. Published about 1817,
      Berlin, in Schlesingersche Buch-und
      Musikhandlung, publ. no. 610.
      This is apparently the copy from
      which the published work was printed,
      and is the composer's autograph. The
      words of the songs are written a
      second time in an unidentified hand.
      Contents listed on cards for the
      Schlesinger edition.
  - LISZT, FRANZ, 1811-1886
    - [Mignon's Lied: Kennst du das Land? Gedicht von Goethe. Music von Franz Liszt] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      [6] p. 34 x 27 cm.
      Vocal score with pianoforte
      accompaniment. At head of p. 1,
      in Hans Bülow's hand: Mscrpt. v.
      Liszt, and Bülow's endorsement, dated
      1892 to Martin Krause. Original
      draft of the song in the later
      version. The words are not
      completely filled in, one measure
      is cancelled. Published,
      together with the first version,
      in Liszt's Musikalische Werke,
      hrsg. von der Franz Liszt-Stiftung,
      VII. Einstimmige Lieder und
      Gesänge, Bd. 2, with full notes
      as to editions and manuscripts.
  - LOEWE, CARL, 1797-1869
    - Frühzeitiger Frühling, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      [2] p. 16 x 22 cm.
      Four-part song, unaccompanied,
      words by Goethe, beginning:
      Tage der Wonne, kommt ihr so
      bald?
      Published in Loewe's Vierstimmige
      Gesänge für S., A., T u. B.,
      seiner Frau componiert. Dresden,
      Paul (Friedel), 1841. Op. 79.
      The words and music are the
      composer's autograph. Title in
      gold letters and an illuminated
      border in colors. At end, in gold
      letters, Göthe und Löwe. The
      decoration is thought to be the work
      of the daughters of Fr. Kugler.
    - Strömt von der hohen steilen Felswand (Box 1, Folder 9)
      [2] p. 17 x 32 cm.
      Song for one voice with piano
      accompaniment. The composer's autograph
      of a fragment from his op. 88,
      Gesang der Geister über den Wassern
      [by Goethe], for four voices (S.A.T.B.)
      the second stanza only, beginning
      Strömt von der hohen steilen Felswand.
      At end: Johann Karl Gottfried Löwe.
  - MENDELSSOHN-BARTHOLDY, FELIX, 1809-1847.
    - Suleika [Op. 57, no. 3], 1841 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph ms., signed.
      [2] p. 29 x 22 cm.
      For solo voice with piano accompaniment.
      At end of p. [2]: "Lepizig 7t Juni 1841.
      Felix Mendelssohn-Bartholdy." Begins:
      Was bedeutet die Bewegnung; words taken
      from Geothe's West-östlicher Divan. First
      published in 1843 as no. 3 of Sechs
      Lieder mit Begleitung des Pianoforte.
      Op. 57. Leipzig, Breitkopf and Härtel.
  - MOESCHINGER, ALBERT, 1897-1985.
    - Katzenpastete, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Autograph ms., signed. Inscribed to Rudolf Jung, 1937 February.
      1 p. 22 x 27 cm.
      Song for voice and piano, on the last four stanzas of Goethe's poem.
  - MÖLLINGER, O.
    - Sechs Gesänge mit Begleitung des Piano-forte comp von O. Möllinger, Lehrer im Gesang und Pianoforte spielen, [1830?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      1p.l., [12] p. 23 x 32 cm.
      Stamps on t.-p.: No. 36, and
      book-stamp, Luise P.v.P., with
      crown.
      Contents:
      1. Schlachtgesang. Gedicht von
      Klopstock: wie erscholl der
      Gang des lauten Heers.
      2. Mailied eines Mädchens.
      Von Voss: Seht den Himmel wie
      heiter.
      3. Dieses Bangen, dieses Sehnen.
      4. Kalge. Gedicht von Sophie
      Mereau: Im sonningen Schimmer.
      5. An die Entfernte. Gedicht von
      Göthe: So hab' ich wirklich dich
      verloren.
      6. Die Sommernacht. Gedicht von
      Klopstock: Wenn der Schimmer von
      dem Monde.
  - NAUMANN, JOHANN GOTTLIEB, 1741-1801.
    - Auf den Auen wandlen wir, 1785 September (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Autograph ms., signed and dated at Copenhagen.
      [2] p. 15 x 21 cm.
      Song for voice and piano, on a poem first published by Bernhard Suphan in Goethe-Jahrbuch, 1890.
      Title from first line.
  - PLÜDDEMANN, MARTIN, 1854-1897.
    - Ritter Kurt's Brautfahrt [by Goethe], 1883 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Autograph ms., signed M.
      Plüddemann 1883.
      [9] p. 34 cm.
      For one voice with pianoforte
      accompaniment. Published about 1893,
      in his Balladen und Gesänge für Bariton
      oder Bass. Nürnberg, Schmid, Bd. 3,
      No. 4. Begins: Mit des Bräutigams
      Behagen.
  - PREYER, GOTTFRIED, 1807-1901
    - Mignon. Dichtung v. Göthe. Musik v. Gfd. Preyer. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Autograph ms., signed
      [3] p. 21 x 28 cm.
      Song for alto or bass voice with piano
      accompaniment, in strophic form.
      Begins: Kennst du das Land? Apparently
      unpublished. Written on six-line music
      manuscript paper ruled in blue, with
      line border in red.
  - [REICHARDT, JOHANN FRIEDRICH], 1752-1814
    - [Jery und Bätely. Singspiel in 1 Akt von Goethe] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Autograph ms. of the songs only.
      [188] p. 34 cm.
      On p. 1: Ouverture zu Bätely und
      Jeri. For solo voices, chorus, and
      orchestra. Full score.
      On wrapper, Henriette Kühne-Harkort.
      Madame Kühne-Harkort was a singer
      who appeared in concert and oratorio
      about 1836 and 1838. She is referred
      to as "Dilettante und echte Künstlerin"
      Cf. Allgemeine musikalische Zeitung,
      Bd. 38, no. 23, col. 765, 1836.
  - RÜFER, PHILIPP, 1810-1891
    - [Meeresstille und glückliche fahrt], 1872 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      [4] p. 32 x 26 cm.
      For four voices with pianoforte
      accompaniment. Two poems by Goethe,
      unfinished, ending with the first
      line of the second poem, Die Nebel
      zerreissen. In pencil, at head of
      p. [1]: Manuscript v. Philipp Rüfer.
      1872. Willi Müller.
  - RUNGENHAGEN, CARL FRIEDRICH, 1778-1851
    - Drey Gedichte von Göthe und Novalis. Musik von C:F: Rungenhagen (Box 2, Folder 16)
      [14] p. 24 x 30 cm.
      The first and third songs are for
      one voice with piano accompaniment,
      the second for soprano, alto, tenor
      and bass, with soprano solo and
      piano accompaniment; the second
      in strophic form. On t.-p.:
      Der Königl. Preuss. ersten Sängerin
      Frau Milder Hauptmann ergebenst
      zugeeignet vom Verfasser.
      1. Gretchen vor einem Andachtsbild
      der Mater Dolorosa, aus Göthe's
      Faust: Ach neige, du Schmerzensreiche.
      2. Trost in Thränen, von Göthe: Wie
      kommts, dass du so traurig bist.
      3. Maria, von Novalis: Ich sehe
      dich in tausend Bildern.
    - Lebensmelodien. Gedicht von A.W. Schlegel. Music von C.F. Rungenhagen., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17)
      [9] p. 24 x 30 cm.
      Three songs, two for one voice with
      piano accompaniment, the third for
      two voices and piano, all in strophic
      form. On t.-p.: Der Königl. Sängerin
      Madame Milder von Componisten. Contents:
      Der Schwan.
      Der Adler.
      Die Tauben.
  - SCHACHNER, JOSEPH, 1816-1876
    - Rondeau pour le Piano-forte sur un theme favori de Robert le Diable composé et tres humble et tres soumis serviteur Jos. Schachner (Box 2, Folder 18)
      1p.l., [23] p. 30 cm.
      Presumably the composer's autograph
      ms., except for the t.-p. which is
      in calligraphic hand, decorated with
      scrolls and flourishes. Robert le Diable,
      an opera by Giacomo Meyerbeer,
      was performed for the first time in 1831.
      "Dédié à Sa Majesté la Reine Caroline
      de Baviére."
  - SCHLEUSSNER
    - Lieder von Schleussner. Eigene Handschrift (Box 2, Folder 19)
      [26] p. 24 x 31 cm.
      Songs for one or two voices, with
      accompaniment for piano or guitar.
      One song, Sieh mich Heil'ger wie
      ich bin, has accompaniment of
      violins, oboe obbligato, viola,
      and bass. The title is in Zelter's
      handwriting, cf. pencil note
      on t.-p. The page references
      for the Goethe songs are to the
      edition pub. by Göschen, Leipzig, 1790.
      1. Unser süsster Beruf [Text von]
      Gotter
      2. Mädel schau mir ins Gesicht [Text
      von] Bürger.
      3. Ein Pilgermädel jung und schön
      [Text von] Bürgers Gedichte, 2., s. 102.
      4. Ich und der Bach: Hier unterm
      stillen Hüttendach [Text von] Werthing.
      5. Willst du frey und lustig gehn
      [Text von] Jacobi.
      6. Dich sanfter Jüngling [Text von]
      Tiedge.
      7. Der Storch bring nun ein Brüderlein
      [Text von] Claudius.
      8. Als ich einige Gräber: Süsser Mohn
      umkränzt [Text] von Soph. Albrecht.
      9. Selma: Sie liebt mich, liebt
      der Auserwählte [Text] von Voss.
      10. Es war ein König in Tule [Von]
      Göthe's Schriften, 7. Bd. Faust, S. 94
      11. Meine Ruh ist hin [Von] Göthe's
      Schriften, 7. Bd. Faust, S. 133.
      12. Freude, schöner Götterfunken
      [Text von Schiller]
      13. Ein Veilchen auf der Wiese stand
      [Von] Göthe's Schriften, 5. Bd. Erwin
      und Elmire, s. 338.
      14. Wer nie in schnöder Wollust
      Schoss [Von] Bürger's Gedichte.
      15. Der Feind ist da, die Schlacht
      beginnt [Text von] Klopstock.
      16. Sieh mich Hielger wie ich bin
      [Text von] Erwin und Elmire v.
      Göthe [two settings]
      17. Que le jour me dure passé
      loin de toi [Anon.]
  - SPOHR, LUDWIG, 1784-1859
    - Bruchstück aus den für England 1852 nachcomponirten recitativen etc. zu seiner Oper "Faust". (Box 2, Folder 20)
      [2] p. 21 x 34 cm.
      For one voice with piano accompaniment.
      A sketch from Act 3, no. 19; the
      words: tobenden Flammen. der
      sterbende grauenvollen Bilder, die
      mich gleich Furien geschrecht im
      Augenblick der höchsten Freude?
      Wie? war vie-[lleicht es meine
      Letzte? die Letzte? ja, sie soll's
      ge]-wesen sien! Hiermit entsage ich
      der Hölle Banden, die mir nicht
      loren! Ihr stolzen Träume, die ihr
      mich verführtet, fahrt hin! ich kenne
      nun die Schranken, die Sterbliche
      nicht überspringen sollen.
      Note at head of p. [1]: Dass dieses
      Manuscriptstück Sporhs eigne
      Handschrift ist, bescheinigt
      dessen Wittwe Marianne Spohr,
      geb. Pfeiffer. Cassel, Nov. 1880.
      With ALS from Ad. Harvier to Carl
      Pollitz, Cassel 6 Nov 1880, forwarding
      this ms. The text as here given varies
      only slightly from that in the published
      score. The music shows slight
      differences throughout.
    - Neue Liebe, neues Leben (von Göthe). Lied für eine Singstimme mit Begleitung des Pianoforte, componirt von L. Spohr. revidirt von Carl Rundnagel, [1858] (Box 2, Folder 21)
      [3] p. 35 cm.
      In caption-title: Componirt 1858
      [footnote:] Letzte Gesangcomposition
      des Meisters. Composed in 1858,
      for the Deutscher Musenalmanach, at the
      request of the editor, Christian Schad.
      cf. Spohr, Selbstbiographie, Bd. 2,
      p. 395-6. According to Goedeke it was
      not published.
  - VOLKMANN, ROBERT, 1815-1883
    - Die Bekehrte von Göthe, für Sopran mit Clavierbegleitung componirt von Robert Volkmann [op. 54] Mit Clavierbegleitung componirt von Robert Volkmann [op. 54], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
      [1], 6. p. 33 cm.
      Begins: Bei dem Glanz der Abendröthe.
      Published by B. Schott's Söhne, Mainz,
      ca. 1867.
  - WAGNER, RICHARD, 1813-1883
    - [Eine Faust Ouvertüre], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Autograph ms., fragment, bars 61-240,
      of the first version, with corrections.
      2 p. 36 x 27 cm. Fragment of sketch
      for the first version of the work,
      completed in 1840 and given the title
      Ouvertüre zu Goethe's 'Faust', Ier Theil.
      This version is also known as Der
      einsame Faust (or: Faust in der
      Einsamkeit); ein Tongedicht für das
      Orchester. Fragment corresponds to
      measures 59-257 of the final version,
      printed by Breitkopf & Härtel in 1855,
      which incorporates major revisions.
  - WEITZMANN, KARL FRIEDRICH, 1808-1880
    - Mignon in Engelskleidern v. Göthe, comp. v. C. Weitzmann., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
      [7] p. 9 x 11 cm.
      Caption-title: Mignon v. Göthe.
      Begins: So lasst mich scheinen. From
      Goethe's Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre.
      Apparently unpublished.
  - ZELTER, CARL FRIEDRICH, 1758-1832
    - An Mignon [and] Wonne der Wehmuth (Box 2, Folder 25)
      [2] p. 27 x 33 cm.
      Caption titles. An Mignon: Ueber
      Thal und Fluss getragen, song for
      one voice with piano accompaniment.
      Words of the first stanza with
      music; second-fourth stanzas at
      bottom of page. At end: Göthe. Mus.
      v. Zelter. Wonne der Wehmuth:
      Trocknet nicht, song for one voice
      with piano accompaniment.
      At end: Göthe. Mus. v. Zelter.
      An Mignon, with the melody as in
      the ms., but with different
      accompaniment, was pub. in Melodien
      zum Schillerschen Musenalmanach,
      1798, and again in Zelter's
      Zwölf Lieder am Klavier zu singen,
      Berlin, 1801, bei G.F. Starke.
      Wonne der Wehmuth is apparently
      unpublished. A second ms., in the
      Preussische Staats-Bibliothek Berlin,
      differs slightly. - cf. Letter from A.
      Kippenberg, Sept. 3, 1931
      [in folder with ms.]
  - UNIDENTIFIED COMPOSERS
    - Gesänge mit Begleitung des Piano-forte, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Manuscript copy of a collection
      of songs wrongly attributed to
      Joh. Fried. Reichardt.
      [23] p. 19 x 34 cm.
      At bottom of t.-p., in another hand,
      Joh. Fried. Reichardt; in pencil,
      Reichardt. A comparison of the
      handwriting with that of Reichardt's
      manuscripts shows it not to be his.
      Reichardt composed music for no. 1
      and no. 8, but his settings differ
      from those given here. None of the
      remaining songs listed in any of his
      published collections. The music for
      "Der König in Thule" is composed by
      Johann George Wilhelm Schneider.
      1. Treulieb: Treulieb ist nimmer
      weit [at end] Tiek Strenbald [i.e.
      from Tieck's romance, Franz
      Sternbalds Wanderungen]
      2. Lied: Süsse Ahndungsschauer
      gleiten [at end] Tiek. Phantasie.
      3. Geistliches Lied: Wenn ich nur
      habe [at end] Novalis.
      4. Sehnsuchtrufen: Holdes holdes
      Sehnsuchtrufen [at end] Tiek
      Sternbald.
      5. An den Erlöser: Löser Sünden
      erlöse mich.
      6. Ballad: Nacht wie so schaurig
      7. An den Erlöser: Du der in Schmach
      und Hohne [at end] Giesebracht [?]
      8. Der König in Tule: Es war ein
      König in Tule [at end] Göthe.
      9. Lied: O alte Heimath süss
      [at end] Tiek
      10. Komm herbei Tod [at end]
      Schakspear
      11. Lied des Aladdin am Grabe
      seiner Mutter: Schlafe Kind im
      Blumenbeet
    - Mignon. Klavierauszug., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
      [55] p. 35 cm.
      For double chorus with piano
      accompaniment, which was originally
      for orchestra. The Requiem für
      Mignon from Goethe's Wilhelm Meister's
      Lehrjahre; begins: Wen bringt ihr
      uns zur stillen Gesellschaft?
    - Nein! Darf ich zu deinem Preise, nach treuer Sänger-weise, ein kleines Lied dir weih'n! (Box 2, Folder 28)
      [3] p. 14 x 18 cm.
      accompaniment Signed, N. Huber. Within
      blind embossed border. "Fanny Miller"
      and "von Göthe" written above title,
      but the text apparently is not by Göthe
    - Sammlung v. Liedern für Guitarre u. Klavier, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
      78 p. of music. 17 x 20 cm.
      Transcriber unknown. Text by Goethe,
      Schiller, and others; music by Zelter,
      Zumsteeg, Harder, and others. Partial
      contents:
      Goethe: 1. An die Erwahlte! (Hand in
      Hand und Lipp auf Lippe).
      5. Stirbt der Fuchs (Nach Mittage sassen
      wir junges Volk)
      6. Frühlings Orachel! (Du prophetscher
      Vogel).
      15. An die Entfernte (So hab ich
      wirklich dich verloren?).
      27. Gedicht [Mignon] (Kennst du das
      Land?) [music by Hausler].
      Schiller: 30. Monolog der Maria Stuart
      (O Dank! Dank diesen freundlich grünen
      Bäumen) [music by Zumsteeg]
      31. Abschieds Lied Johannes aus Schillers
      Jungfrau von Orleans (Lebt wohl irh Berge,
      ihr geliebten Triften) [music by
      Zumsteeg]
      One sheet of music for piano [?] laid in.